Guide to the Julien Cornell Papers Relating to Ezra Pound
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Julien Cornell papers relating to Ezra Pound
1945-1965
YCAL MSS 176
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.88
(5 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence and professional files relating to Cornell's representation of Ezra Pound in the initial stages of the U.S. government's case against him for treason. In addition to Ezra and Dorothy Pound, correspondents include T. S. Eliot, Ernest Hemingway, James Laughlin, Arthur Moore, Omar Pound, Mary de Rachewiltz, and Olga Rudge. Topics include Pound's physical and mental condition in 1945-46; the treason charge against him; the efforts to have him declared mentally incompetent to stand trial; his court appearances; the use of the Alien Property Act against Dorothy Pound; and conditions at St. Elizabeth's Hospital. The collection also contains legal documents relating to the Pound case, including psychiatric evaluation reports; notices of court dates; material relating to a writ of habeas corpus prepared by Cornell in 1948; and transcripts of Pound's radio broadcasts from Rome.
Cornell, Julien D., 1910-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Julien Cornell (1933 Law), 1966.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 19: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
JULIEN CORNELL, 1910-1994
Julien Cornell was born in Brooklyn in 1910 and graduated from Swarthmore College in 1930. He received his law degree from Yale Law School in 1933 and opened a practice in Manhattan shortly thereafter.
A member of the Society of Friends, Cornell had a strong interest in civil liberties law, and during World War II he handled many cases for conscientious objectors to the draft. He was Counsel for the American Civil Liberties Union National Lawyers National Committee on Conscientious Objection (ACLU-NCCO) and served as chair of the Lawyers Committee of the Metropolitan Board for Conscientious Objectors. During this time, Cornell published The Conscientious Objector and the Law (1943), and Conscience and the State (1945), and served as an expert consultant on the issue of conscientious objection and assignment to alternate service in the CPS (Civilian Public Service).
In November 1945, his friend James Laughlin of New Directions Press contacted him and asked him if he would be willing to represent Ezra Pound, who had been arrested in Italy and charged with treason for broadcasts he made over Rome Radio in 1942 and 1943. Public opinion was strongly against Pound, but Cornell agreed, as he "always enjoyed fighting for the underdog" and did not consider that the speeches met the American legal standard for treason. After meeting with Pound, however, and consulting with several of his old friends, Cornell resolved to enter a plea of insanity for his client. Hearings were held and expert witnesses retained, and on February 13, 1946, a jury impanelled by Judge Bolitha Laws returned a verdict of "unsound mind." While Cornell had hoped to secure Pound's release on bail once he had been adjudged insane, Pound was remanded to Federal custody at St. Elizabeth's Federal Hospital for the Insane in Washington, D.C., where he remained until August 1958.
Cornell moved his law practice to Central Valley, New Jersey in 1950, but continued to offer legal and strategic advice to Pound and his representatives. He was the author of New World Primer (1947), which advocated a world federal government and was published by Laughlin's New Directions Press; The Trial of Ezra Pound (1966), which reproduced a selection of the legal documents relating to the Pound case; and A Tale of Treasure Trove (1977), a collection of essays that included "The Last Years of Ezra Pound," a restatement of Cornell's personal belief in Pound's insanity.
Julien Cornell married Virginia Scratton in 1932; the couple had two sons and two daughters, all of whom survived him. After his retirement from active practice, he traveled extensively in Europe and continued to pursue his interests in local history and home winemaking. Cornell died in Goshen, New York, on December 2, 1994.
Scope and Contents
The Julien Cornell Papers Relating to Ezra Pound document Cornell's role as Ezra Pound's defense attorney during the initial stages of Pound's trial on charges of treason. The papers span the dates 1945-1965 and are organized into two series: Series I. Ezra Pound Correspondence Files and Series II, 'U. S. v. Ezra Pound' Case File.
Series I, Ezra Pound Correspondence Files, has been organized into two subseries: Individual Correspondent Files and Third-Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. While the bulk of the correspondence concerns Cornell's legal efforts on Pound's behalf from 1945 through 1948, there is also documentation of his assistance to Dorothy Pound; a few related legal cases; and attempts by others to gain Pound's release or to create favorable publicity about him.
Cornell's first contact with the Pound case was through their mutual friend James Laughlin, whose correspondence is located in folders 14-19. Topics include Cornell's first meeting with Pound and his conviction that Pound was "under a mental cloud;" Cornell's and Laughlin's agreement that a plea of insanity would be "Pound's best chance of escape," given that "Pound appears crazy;" and Cornell's unsuccessful efforts to free Pound on bail. Other subjects include legal matters concerning Pound titles published by New Directions Press, and real estate contracts and ski lift investments by Laughlin at Alta Ski Area.
During this period, Cornell began to correspond with the Pounds' London solicitor, Arthur V. Moore of Shakespear & Parkyn (Box 1, folders 24-28). Moore, who had known the Pounds for many years, attempted to qualify Cornell's opinion of Pound's sanity as early as December 10, 1945: "undoubtedly he seemed to his wife more normal than he is....and to you much more unbalanced than he is....he is a person requiring much understanding, and to the average man he appears crazy." Cornell and Moore corresponded on several aspects of Pound's defense, including Cornell's plan to have counsel appointed for him if the case went to trial and the difficulty of obtaining Pound's cooperation in any defense strategy. The letters also deal with Dorothy Pound's ambiguous legal status, as she had relinquished her British citizenship upon marrying Pound, while the United States had categorized her as an enemy alien. Both lawyers detail the difficulties they faced in their efforts to clarify her nationality and to make her income available to her.
In turn, Moore put Cornell in contact with both Dorothy Pound and her son, Omar Pound. Omar Pound's telegrams and letters to Cornell are located in Box 2, folders 51-52, and concern his efforts to obtain compassionate leave from the U.S. Army and his questions about Pound's condition. A cable dated January 3, 1946 forwards his APO address and asks "Are health reports legal strategy or genuine stop."
Dorothy Pound's letters to Cornell are located in Box 1, folders 32-44. The earliest letters, written from Rapallo, detail her attempts to be allowed into the United States to see her husband and her worries about his mental status: "my presence would be of great help to him: I know and understand the very delicately balanced creature so well," she wrote in December of 1945. When she did see Pound, in July 1946, she reported that she found him "very nervous and jumpy" and that "he holds my hands most of the time during my visits," which she judged uncharacteristic of him. Much of her correspondence with Cornell, however, concerns financial matters, both her own and Pound's, for whom she had been named "Committee" by the court. Another frequent topic is her desire to return to Italy with Pound, which Cornell believed to be an unrealistic goal. Also in the collection are her refusals to support the 1948 appeal of habeas corpus, and a 1957 letter declining an ACLU-financed appeal.
Ezra Pound's letters to Cornell are found in Box 2, folders 45-50. The earliest, from January and February of 1946, are somewhat disjointed reports on his own mental condition: "absolute futility of might have been-- coherent areas constantly invaded aiuto Pound," reads the first. "Problem now is not to go stark screamin hysteric," he wrote a week later, and "young doctors absolutely useless." By the middle of March, however, he was sending firmly worded business letters to Cornell on a variety of financial matters, including the transfer of publication rights for Personae to New Directions Press and instructions on fees and payments: "$25 per poem has been the minimum anthology fee for years and years with $50 for a canto." Pound also directed Cornell to send payments and messages to Olga Rudge and to their daughter, Mary de Rachewiltz, for whom he wished to execute a power of attorney. There are few letters after 1946, although folder 50 contains a typed statement of Pound's "Position" on his political views and on the radio broadcasts.
Cornell's efforts to carry out his client's wishes brought him into contact with Olga Rudge, whose correspondence is located in Box 2, folders 55-56. Rudge, like Dorothy Pound, urged Cornell to seek Pound's quick return to Italy, and her first letters argued that his mother's illness in Rapallo would be a suitable rationale for his release. By January 1947, however, Rudge had become concerned about Pound's mental state and angered at Dorothy Pound's control of his affairs, and sent Cornell a lengthy letter outlining Pound's personal and marital history and announcing her intention to take "steps to regain my place near E.P" and to care for him after his release. Cornell noted that her questions "were quite beyond my ability to answer. The personal relations between you, Mr. Pound, and Mrs. Pound, are a matter for the three of you to settle." He also undertook to dissuade Rudge from publishing a selection of Pound's radio broadcasts ( If this be treason....: Siena, 1948). Later correspondence deals with Rudge's critiques of his efforts to free Pound; her attempts to publicize Pound's cause in Italy; and the idea of publishing a larger selection of the broadcasts.
Several correspondents represented in Series I were personal friends of Pound whom Cornell queried about Pound's mental state, including E. E. Cummings, T. S. Eliot, Ernest Hemingway, Archibald MacLeish, and Allen Tate. While Tate and MacLeish both declined comment, Hemingway responded with a warm letter declaring that Pound "has not been normal mentally for at least the past ten years" and claiming that he heard the broadcasts while with the American troops in Europe but "never felt any bitterness toward Ezra Pound." Cummings responded with a declaration of friendship and appreciation for Pound.
The letters between T. S. Eliot and Cornell are housed in Box 1, folders 6-10, and reflect Eliot's continuing concern for Pound's welfare and his careful judgements about strategies to turn public opinion in favor of Pound's release. Eliot cautioned Cornell against publication of the radio broadcasts, fearing that "the amount of irritation which Ezra's incidental remarks might cause" would outweigh any possible benefit. He also argued at length against publication of the trial record, which Cornell thought might sway the public in Pound's favor. Eliot believed that it would convince the public that Pound should be permanently confined, and also that Pound would be upset by it: "To have his economic theories publicly branded as the ravings of a paranoic could hardly be indifferent to him unless he were a great deal further removed from contact with reality than I believe him to be."
Cornell was eager to obtain favorable public notice for his client whenever possible. He wrote encouragingly to Léonie Adams of the Bollingen Prize Committee in response to her suggestion that they might award the prize to Pound; he negotiated tactfully phrased footnotes with Bennett Cerf and wrote letters of correction to newspapers whenever Pound was referred to as "guilty of treason." However, he often found himself discouraging "undesirable publicity" such as Charles Norman's 1946 book project, and the public relations efforts made by Tiffany Thayer of the Fortean Society and the "currency reformist Clara Studer. A 1957 letter from Moore refers to his "files crowded with proposals from well-meaning people for securing the release of Ezra Pound."
Other correspondents include Pound's old friends Viola Baxter Jordan and Ida B. Mapel and Dr. Winfred Overholser, Superintendent of St. Elizabeth's Hospital.
The subseries Third-Party Correspondence is alphabetically arranged by author and consists of letters by Clara Studer, Willis A. Overholser and Jose Garcia Villa to different recipients.
Series II, U. S. v. Ezra Pound Case File, is housed in Boxes 2-4 and has been organized into three subseries: Chronological Correspondence File; Chronological Legal Documents; and Other Case Material. The first subseries, Chronological Correspondence File, consists primarily of business and official correspondence and associated documentation exchanged between Cornell and others with official roles in the case. These include Judge Bolitha Laws and other officers of the court; employees of the Departments of Justice and of State; the psychiatrists who were members of the expert witnesses panel, Wendell Muncie and Theron Caudle; and staff of St. Elizabeth's Hospital for the Insane. Subjects include trial dates and deadlines for the filing of motions and briefs; Cornell's business trips to Washington, D.C. and visits with his client; the psychiatric reports on Pound's mental state; and the legal status of Dorothy Pound, who had been listed by the government as an enemy alien. Box 3, folder 84 contains correspondence relating to Cornell's proposal to file an appeal of habeas corpus on behalf of Pound, which was withdrawn when Dorothy Pound objected. Cornell's later correspondence with the American Civil Liberties Union on the Pound case is located in folder 88.
The second subseries, Chronological Legal Documents, contains Cornell's working copies of all official court documents pertaining to the case, from the initial Grand Jury indictment of Pound on treason charges through the aborted 1948 habeas corpus appeal. Other Case Material includes miscellaneous notes about and by Pound; papers relating to Cornell's billing and expenses in the case; and a complete set of transcripts of Pound's Rome Radio Broadcasts, four of which formed the basis for the charge of treason.
Alien property -- United States; American literature -- 20th Century; Competency to stand trial -- United States; Forensic psychiatry -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Treason -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda; World War, 1939-1945 -- Radio broadcasting and the war; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; Cornell, Julien D., 1910-; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997; Laws, Bolitha (Bolitha James), 1891-1958; Moore, Arthur V.; Muncie, Wendell, 1897-; Overholser, Winfred, 1892-1964; Pound, Dorothy; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Political and social views; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Psychology; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Relations with women; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Pound, Omar S., 1926-; Rachewiltz, Mary de, 1925-; Rudge, Olga, 1895-1996; United States. Office for Emergency Management. Office of Alien Property Custodian; United States. Department of Justice. Office of the Attorney General; United States. District Court (District of Columbia); Saint Elizabeths Hospital (Washington, D.C.)
- Ezra Pound Correspondence Files, 1945-1965; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Ezra Pound Correspondence Files, is organized into two alphabetically arranged subseries: Individual Correspondent Files and Third-Party Correspondence. Both contain incoming letters and retained copies of outgoing letters.
  - INDIVIDUAL CORRESPONDENT FILES
    - Adams, Léonie, 1949, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cerf, Bennett, 1946-65 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cummings, E. E., 1945-48 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cummings, Marion, 1945 Dec 17-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Edwards, John, 1956-58 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Eliot, T. S., 1947-48 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes letter expressing concern over Pound's lack of freedom at St. Elizabeth's.
    - Eliot, T. S., 1950-51 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Eliot, T. S., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Eliot, T. S., 1953-1954 Jul (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Eliot, T. S., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes TLS from Valerie Eliot, 1965 Sep 17
    - Hemingway, Ernest, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Jordan, Viola, 1945-46 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lamont, Helen, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Laughlin, James, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Laughlin, James, 1946 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Laughlin, James, 1946 Mar-May (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Laughlin, James, 1946 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Laughlin, James, 1947 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Laughlin, James, 1947 Mar-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Liveright Publishing Corporation, 1945-47 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - MacGregor, Robert M., 1955 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Mapel, Ida, 1945-47 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Moore, Arthur V., 1945 Oct-Nov (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes 2 TLS from Arthur Moore to James Laughlin, 1945 Oct 9; 1945 Nov 29
    - Moore, Arthur V., 1945 Dec (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Moore, Arthur V., 1946 Feb-Mar (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Moore, Arthur V., 1946 Apr-Dec (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Moore, Arthur V., 1947-65 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Norman, Charles, 1946-57 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Olson, Charles, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Overholser, Winfred, 1945-53 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1945-1946 Jun (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1946 Jul (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1946 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 34)
      With copies of DP's will
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1946 Oct (Box 1, Folder 35)
      With extensive financial accounts for DP
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1946 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1947 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1947 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1947 May (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1947 Jun-Sep (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1947 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1948 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1948 Apr-Dec (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1949-57 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1945 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 45)
      With TL carbon of EP to Shakespear & Parkyn, 1945 Oct 5
      With property receipt signed from Gallinger Hospital
    - Pound, Ezra, 1946 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1946 Mar-Apr (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1946 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1946 Jul-Nov (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1947-48 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Pound, Omar, 1945-46; 1966 (Box 2, Folder 51-52)
    - de Rachelwiltz, Mary, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Rice, Virginia, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      With copies of office correspondence Personae royalties, 1941
    - Rudge, Olga, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Rudge, Olga, 1947-54 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Santayana, George, 1945 Nov 29 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Shakespear & Parkyn
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Arthur V. Moore
    - Spencer, Theodore, 1946 Dec (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Studer, Clara, 1945-47 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Tate, Allen, 1945-46 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Thayer, Tiffany, 1945-48 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Zabel, Morten Dauwen, 1950 Mar 5 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Studer, Clara, to Pound, Ezra, 1945 Dec 13 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Overholser, Willis A., to Mapel, Ida, 1939 Sep 25 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Villa, Jose Garcia, to Laughlin, James, 1946 Jul 31 (Box 2, Folder 65)
- U. S. v. Ezra Pound Case File, Series II
  - CHRONOLOGICAL CORRESPONDENCE FILE
    - Correspondence, 1945 Nov (Box 2, Folder 66)
      Includes letters concerning psychiatric examination for EP and passport problems of DP; official notices of trial dates
    - Correspondence, 1945 Dec 3-6 (Box 2, Folder 67-68)
      Includes letters concerning psychiatric examination and EP's history (to Dr. Wendell Muncie) and "eneny alien" designations of DP and EP
    - Correspondence, 1945 Dec 7-10 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Includes TLS from Judge Bolitha Laws accepting Dr. Wendell Muncie as examiner for EP
    - Correspondence, 1945 Dec 11-14 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Includes TLS by Wendell Muncie declaring EP "unfit to stand trial" and typescript carbon of official psychiatric report
    - Correspondence, 1945 Dec 17-31 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Includes copy of psychiatric report
    - Correspondence, 1946 Jan 7-31 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Includes letters from Theron Caudle, Judge Bolitha Laws, Wendell Muncie; copy of psychiatric report; notifications of court dates
    - Correspondence, 1946 Feb (Box 2, Folder 73)
      Includes letters from Theron Caudle and Wendell Muncie
    - Correspondence, 1946 Mar (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Includes letters on release of EP and DP funds
    - Correspondence, 1946 Apr-May (Box 2, Folder 75)
      Includes TLS from Samuel A. Silk concerning EP canteen privileges
    - Correspondence, 1946 Jun (Box 2, Folder 76)
      Includes letters concerning the reprinting of "Don't of an Imagiste"
    - Correspondence, 1946 Jul (Box 2, Folder 77)
      Includes letters concerning Alien Property Act; correspondence with New York Herald Tribune
    - Correspondence, 1946 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 78)
      Includes letters concerning release of funds
    - Correspondence, 1947 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 79-80)
      Includes TLS from Theron Caudle; TLS from Claude B. Cross on Douglas Chandler treason case
    - Correspondence, 1947 Mar-Dec (Box 2, Folder 81-83)
      Includes TLS from Claude B. Cross and letters concerning release of funds
    - Correspondence, 1948 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 84)
      Includes letters concerning filing and withdrawal of appeal of habeas corpus
    - Correspondence, 1948 May-Sep (Box 2, Folder 85)
      Includes letters concerning Saturday Review of Literature article
    - Correspondence, 1953-54 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      Includes ALS from Frederick Morgan and TL carbon reply on possible grounds of appeal
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 87)
      Includes 2 TLS from Douglas Hammond concerning strategy for Pound's release
    - Correspondence, 1956-58 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Includes ACLU letters and press release
    - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      Includes requests for permission to publish
  - CHRONOLOGICAL LEGAL DOCUMENTS
    - Grand Jury indictment for treason (3 copies), 1945 Oct (Box 3, Folder 90-91)
    - Application for bail: Affadavit, exhibits, psychiatric report and memorandum of law in favor; prosecution memorandum of opposition to bail, 1945 Nov (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Transcript of testimony in U. S. v. Ezra Pound, 1946 Feb (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Powers of attorney for Cornell by EP (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Motion for bail, notice, and argument; government's reply in opposition to motion, 1947 Jan (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Petition for Habeas corpus, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 96-98)
  - OTHER CASE MATERIAL
    - Notes on Ezra Pound's history, especially the months after his arrest, 1945 Nov 20 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Notes, drafts, and tables of billable hours spent on the Pound case, 1945-46, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 100)